<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Alarm to the officers and souldiers of the armies of England, Scotland, and Ireland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8339</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12326261</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12326261</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 931:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Alarm to the officers and souldiers of the armies of England, Scotland, and Ireland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated: March, 1660.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Scotland. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Ireland. --  Army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Alarum TO THE OFFICERS and SOULDIERS OF THE ARMIES OF <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen, and Fellow-Souldiers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is an old and true ſaying, That Standers by do often ſee more than the Gameſter: And having been out of play for ſome time, I have perhaps diſcovered more than many of your ſelves who do not dive in ſecrets of State, but are content onely to take care how you may receive the pay. I have been engaged in one and the ſame Cauſe and Quarrel with you againſt the late King and his Sons, during which time I obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d very many miraculous providences of God in ſeveral conflicts and bloody Battels, honoured with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Victories, God owning an Army which conſiſted of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of low eſtate, condition, knowledge, or education either in Politick or Military art; when on the other ſide, I ſaw very
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59567:2"/> numerous and potent Armies of the late King and his Sons (who conſiſted of moſt of the Noble and Gentry of the three Nations, very expert both in knowledge and education of that nature) to be by thoſe deſpicable ones abſolutely vanquiſhed, and thereupon the late King brought to Juſtice, and hitherto all the endeavours of his Sons blaſted and diſ-appointed. If you pleaſe to look back, and remember all thoſe ſignal Victories and deliverances, and what thereupon you promiſed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to do for theſe poor afflicted Nations, which in few words and ſubſtance was, that before you would ſuffer your ſelves to be diſ-banded or divided, you would ſee the Government of theſe Nations eſtabliſhed upon the juſt and ſecure fundamentals and conſtitutions of freedome and ſafety to the people, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as they were Men and Chriſtians, and that in the wayes of a Commonwealth and Free-ſtate Government, without a King, ſingle perſon, or Houſe of Lords.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not at this time minde how far you have gone aſtray from that Engagement, ſeeing that moſt of you have repented and returned to your duties: But I ſhall onely by ſounding this Alarm, endeavour to render you ſenſible of the eminent danger which hangs over your heads, and of your beſt friends of the three Nations: And in the firſt place tell you what the old and new enemies the Cavaliers do now ſay of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and late actions. Secondly, what many honeſt and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber people of the Presbyterian judgement think. Thirdly, What danger your beſt friends ſcornfully called Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth-men, and Fanatiques, do fore-ſee concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tranſactions in the three Nations. And laſtly, my own ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations and ſeaſonable advice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Cavaliers do confidently affirm that your Generals late actions do ſufficiently demonſtrate that the bottome of his intention tends only to bring <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> to be King of theſe Nations, grounding the ſame upon ſeveral reaſons: As firſt (ſay they) did he not intend the ſame, he would never (after ſo many Declarations and Proteſtations to be true to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which in ſcorn they call the <hi>Rump</hi>) have the 11. of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> laſt, ſent them ſuch an impoſing Letter, and thereupon (without any order from them) marched with their Army to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59567:2"/> 
               <hi>London,</hi> then eſteemed and made by him (in deſtroying their Gates, &amp;c.) their implacable enemies, and at night ſuffered ſo many bone-fires and ringing of Bels, and publickly drinking healths to the King and a free Parliament, ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng and burning of Rumps, hearing and ſeeing his Maſters in open ſtreet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Murtherers and Rebels, and that in a moſt vile and diſſolute manner, and all this in the preſence of the Army; a thing (ſay they) not to be paralleld in any Hiſtorie of ages paſt, and beſides, without Orders of his Maſters, quartered himſelf an Army amongſt their Enemies till the 21 of the ſaid Month, during which time, he feaſted daily at moſt of the Kings friends and admitted them to him with great reſpects and affection, without returning to <hi>White-hall,</hi> although ſeveral times invited thereunto by his Maſters.</p>
            <p>Secondly, (ſay they) that although by his Letters and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal promiſes he had engaged to them that in caſe they would effect what was contained in the ſaid Letter, he would be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and ſtill be their ſervants (notwithſtanding which he was ſo far from performing the ſame, that although they had within the the time by him limited fulfilled in all things what in that Letter was impoſed upon them, yet not regarding nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſaid Letter, nor verbal promiſe, and without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting (in the leaſt) any of his Maſters, who ſome of them had ventured their all to ſecure him from being ruined by <hi>Lrmberts</hi> Army) your ſaid General (ſay they further) cauſed his Army upon the 21. of the ſaid Month, to march back to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there admits the ſecluded Members to ſit in the Parliament Houſe, moſt of whom he abſolutely knew to be for the reſtoration of <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> (who they call King, and again at night ſuffer Bone-fires and ringing of Bells, and his ſaid Maſters, and others of their friends to be as much, or more abuſed, and vilified, than they were upon the 11. at night of the ſaid Month; whereupon the Cavaliers do conclude (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof aſſured) that your ſaid General in like manner would ſurprize them, and then bring in the King upon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and then give the ſame reaſon for his ſo doing, as he did after he had admitted the ſecluded Members, to wit, the reaſon of not diſcovering the ſame, was becauſe he knew they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59567:3"/> hated them, and would have endeavoured to hinder their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To demonſtrate further (ſay they) that the ſaid General will bring their King, let any rational man conſider, whether he can have any other deſign, ſeeing he hath ſuffered the ſaid ſecluded Members to releaſe Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> and his party, and to diſcharge their Sequeſtrations, and to ſit and vote with them in Parliament: And beſides, although he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how ſeveral of the ſaid ſecluded Members have daily mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Houſe againſt the Government of a Free-ſtate, and for King, Lords, and Commons, and how they have in order thereunto, voted the Covenant to be <hi>de novo</hi> printed, read, and ſet up in every Church of the Nation, whereby they evidently acknowledge the late Kings Poſterity, yet he ſuffered the ſame as likewiſe to be maintained in the Houſe that none but Jeſuits and Prieſts are for Free-ſtate Government. And to evidence further, that the General is reſolved upon that point, Obſerve (ſay the Cavalier) who he cauſeth to be impriſoned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, put out, and put in the Army; to wit, Commonwealth men impriſoned, and turned out of the Army and Garriſons in the three Nations, and Royaliſts taken in Arms at <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight releaſed, and ſeveral others of that ſtamp entruſted with eminent places in Army and Garriſons in the three Nations.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, His countenancing the raiſing of the Militia of City and Country, entruſting the management thereof to moſt of the Kings friends, the ſaid Militia being raiſed and formed to no other end than murther, to deſtroy the Army, in whom (the Cavaliers ſay) the General cannot well confide in, as to bring his deſigns to perfect maturity. And that the ſame was deſigned in <hi>Scotland</hi> long ſince. Obſerve how peaceable they are there, and how the Iriſh Army, have proceeded anſwerable to himſelf: And beſides, ſay ſome of them (being Officers of the late Kings Army) who had been with him ſince his coming to <hi>London,</hi> and offered their ſervice to him, which they ſaid, he accepted, and told them he would before it were long be in a capacity to give them imployment; much more of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which for brevity ſake I omit, onely this one thing more, which very much increaſes their hopes, and that is, ſay they,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59567:3"/> what ſignifies the peaceable return of the Kings friends from their Exile, as Alderman <hi>Bonch</hi> and many others, who had been ſo long fugitives, if the return of the King was not likewiſe intended? And further what doth ſignifie that proviſo in that Act of diſſolution concerning the Lords being a part of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> if there muſt be a Commonwealth?</p>
            <p>As for the ſober Presbyterians, they do of late begin to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the ſaid General, whom (ſay they) gives ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and to his old and new rigid Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, who for certain truth are at this juncture of time at work in arming themſelves in all parts of the three Nations, and will upon a ſudden come like a flood upon you, and the reſt of the engaged party in the Nations, and ſo conquer all by force of Arms; and then what muſt or can be expected to follow, but onely abſolute ruine, for undoubtedly (ſay they) <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> will bring with him Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and the reſt of that Hierarchy, and we ſhall then be accounted no other by them but Sectarians and Phanatiques, and be in the ſame predicament, or worſe for ſervice, than thoſe who are ſo called; and ſay they, muſt not expect to be better uſed than they. And beſides, his Mother the Queen will come, which infallibly will bring with her Jeſuits, Prieſts, and Monks of all ſorts, whereby Popery will <hi>(cum privilegio)</hi> be again re-admitted in the Nation; ſo that they conſider, that if the General and your ſelves do not ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily prevent the ſame, that the Cauſe ſo much contended for, together with the intereſt of good people will ſink, and be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt, and ſo your Harveſt will end in chaffe, and you, and them be carried back through a red Sea of blood in the land of Bondage and miſery, there to ſerve and bear the heavy yoke of one who will not forget that which hath as well been acted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his late Father the King, as againſt himſelf; it being the common talk of the Cavaliers that the Presbyterians brought his Father to the Block, and the Independents cut off his Head.</p>
            <p>As to your beſt friends which have bled with you, and prayed for you, and who have been conſtant aſſertors of the cauſe and intereſt of the good people of theſe Nations againſt Kingſhip, ſingle perſons, &amp; houſe of Lords, they all of one voyce conclude,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59567:4"/> that (under God) there is no other Bulwork of defence againſt the return of Monarchy but the Army, which now they ſee to be abſolutely deſigned for deſtruction by disbanding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, or elſe what meaneth the new Militia now ſetled and intruſted in the hands of perſons almoſt all enemies to a Free-ſtate Government, ſeveral of the ſecluded Members both in the Houſe, and out of the Houſe ſpeaking it openly, as likewiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Commiſſioners of City and Country which have been heard in their Cabals affirm, that as ſoon as their Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaes are ſetled, they will quickly break the Rogues, meaning you, to whom they can ſcarce afford ſo good language; and moreover they hope that the Supreme Authority being once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in the Councel of State as now it is, that the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel will by ſubtil means and practiſes with the General gain him to condeſcend to the disbanding moſt of you, to the end that the intended new Parliament may be able (with more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility) to bring the deſign now in hand to perfection, which in plain Engliſh is to bring <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> to be King: And that which your ſaid friends do thereupon apprehend to follow in order to yours and theirs deſtruction is, Firſt, if you can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by your enemies to admit <hi>Charles</hi> to be King upon any conditions, then reſt aſſured that he will not want an Army, and ſpecially ſuch an one as brought his Father to the Block, and kept him in Exile ſo many years; therefore the firſt work will be to disband you, and ſo leave you to the mercy and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of thoſe that by force you have ſubdued, who in revenge will (without any doubt) take opportunity afterwards to hang many of you, and baniſh others as Rebels and Traytors, or at leaſt caſt you in noyſome Dungeon, but that onely will not ſatisfie their cruelty, but be ſure they will have all your eſtates and deſtroy your Wives and Children, and perſecute you, and, your friend unto death, you may therefore (ſay they) with eaſe diſcern whether it be your intereſt or ſecurity to bring the Nation back under the old bondage of Kings, or elſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and defend a Commonwealths Government, the difference is plain, the one will deſtroy you and your friends, and the other will protect you both, and you will be ſure under a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth not to want as long as any of you ſhall live, nor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59567:4"/> your Wives and Children: And you will be ſure alſo not to become your enemies ſlaves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you ſhould be ſo fooled as to be perſwaded to admit of the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> to return upon any termes, then you will be reputed the moſt perfidious Army that breaths, in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the engagements &amp; promiſes you have made to the contrary, and ſo render all the blood ſpilt, and treaſure exhauſted of no effect; and thereupon give cauſe to the children unborn to curſe ſuch a generation of men as then you would be reputed. But ſayes your friends, If you do withſtand it, and leave the ſucceſs to God, then you will have done your parts as Engliſh men and Chriſtians, and will in after Ages be eſteemed faithful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots, and Aſſertors of your Countrie Liberties, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of yourſelves and poſterities. And ſay they, when the late King had near a hundred thouſand men in Field and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, you were not afraid, and whenſoever you encountred with any part thereof, God ſtrengthned your hearts and hands, and gave you ſeveral Victories to the abſolute overthrowing of them all in the three Nations; therefore they wiſh you courage and bleſſing from on High, and do heartily pray that God may go along with you in diſappointing your enemies, who as yet make no uſe of weapons, ſave of their venemous and lying tongues.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you ſhould be ſo deluded, as to admit the ſaid <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> to be King, then your friends deſire you further to conſider that beſides the foreſaid ruine upon yourſelves and them, what further ruine will attend the three Nations by ſuch admiſſion: Firſt, his late Fathers numerous debts which he contracted in the War which he ſo violently proſecuted againſt the Parliament from the year 1641. till his death, together with all the Arrears of his Armies, and ſalaries of his Court-officers, and meneal ſervants, which without doubt will amount to as much, or more, as the Parliament expended in their defence in that War, muſt be paid and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſaid <hi>Charles Stuarts</hi> own debts contracted here and in <hi>Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> during the ſpace of about ſeventeen years, with likewiſe the ſalaries of his Court-officers, and meneal ſervants, together with the Arrears of his Armies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59567:5"/> which he had in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> all which will be expected to be paid, and which without doubt will far exceed the debts of his Father.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Queen his Mother with the ſalaries of her Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and ſervants, beſides her great Dowry and Arrears thereof muſt likewiſe be paid and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, All the debt of his Brother and Siſter.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, His Court, and theirs, with all dependences muſt be ſet up anew here, furniſhed and maintained with all ſorts of rich Furniture and Jewels, gold and ſilver plate of all ſorts, and all other utenſils as glorious as ever his Father.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Thoſe Dukes, Earls, Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, and other of his, and Fathers party, whoſe eſtates real and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal have been ſold, and diſpoſed by Authority of Parliament, either muſt be reſtored, or ſatisfaction given them for the ſame, but ſpecially for the perſonal eſtate which can never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. All which coſt and charges, if duely conſidered, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all manner of debts owing by the ſaid Family, and carefully calculated, muſt amount to many Millions, ſo that if the Taxes, and other Impoſt now yearly paid in the three Nations ſhould be doubled for twenty years to come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, would not be ſufficient to ſatisfie, and anſwer the ſame.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Whereas the Cavaliers do ſay, That if the Lands of the late King, Queen, &amp;c. and of their party ſhould be reſtored, that it would anſwer a great part of the ſaid Court expences, and ſatisfie thoſe perſons to which it is anſwered, admitting the ſame could be effected, yet none of thoſe debts could thereby be ſatisfied, for it cannot be expected a poſſibility ever to ſettle theſe three Nations upon any condition of a laſting peace, if there be any ravilling and queſtioning the titles of thoſe Lands ſold and diſpoſed by Parliament, conſidering in what manner the Proprieties have been altered ſince thoſe ſails or diſpoſals either by buildings, incloſures and joynings their Lands to them by Mortgages, Intails, and other ſettlements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Marriages, and otherwiſe, that the preſent occupier of moſt part thereof were never ingaged in the War having paid for the ſame fourteen, fifteen, and ſixteen years purchaſe in ready
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59567:5"/> money, which if taken away, or reſtored, will kindle a more violent fire of War in the three Nations, than the firſt.</p>
            <p>And before I give you my advice, and ſo conclude, Give me leave to tell you my particular obſervations, as one who daily is converſant with perſons of divers judgements.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I have certain knowledge (and your ſelves, if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented will finde it too true) that the now Militia of <hi>London,</hi> do intend to bring in <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> one before they do it, as I have divers times, and very lately heard ſome of them boaſt, that they will ſerve you (who are quartered among them) as the <hi>Danes</hi> were of old; that is, in the night in your beds, cut your throats; and in immitation of that act, they make no queſtion but the Country will execute the like upon your fellows quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with them: And truly I have heard ſeveral of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Country ſay as much.</p>
            <p>Secondly, What meaneth the Officers of the Militia when upon the Guard, to go to Tavern and there drink the Kings health, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you do not ſtop your ears, you may as well as my ſelf, underſtand and take notice of the daily threatning of the Enemy when their King is come what they will do to your ſelves and friends, but ſpecially to thoſe faithful Patriots, which under God, have been a ſtrong Bulwark againſt their raged fury, their villanies committed and acted before your faces up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 11. and 21. of <hi>February</hi> at night in <hi>London,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in moſt places of the Nation, may ſerve to convince you that their ſentences againſt you and them are already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and want nothing but execution: If you do not withſtand them ſpeedily, your and their eſtates are already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of, there wants but the Kings coming to put them in actual poſſeſſion. Have not you ſeen already a Catalogue of the names of ſeveral faithful Patriots printed and publiſhed, and cried upon the Exchange, and about the ſtreets, in order to prepare the Rabble to maſſacre them; there is no doubt to be made, but many of your ſelves and other friends to the publick Cauſe, are deſigned for a Sacrifice at their Kings coming, ſome of you may have fair promiſes made of being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and rewarded: If you will ſell, or rather betray the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59567:6"/> Cauſe and Liberties of your Country by admitting him; but that you may not be decoyed or trappanned to truſt your Enemy upon any promiſe of that nature, let me relate a ſhort, and very true Hiſtory of a Governour, who had been entruſted with the command of a ſtrong Frontier Garriſon, and the Enemy who very much aimed at it, as being of great advantage of entrance into the Country, cauſed ſome overture to be made to the ſaid Governour for the betraying the ſame into their hands; whereupon conditions were agreed, by which the ſaid Governour was not onely to have a great ſumme of money as a reward, but likewiſe was promiſed to be continued in his Command, and otherwiſe nobly rewarded: the time being appointed for him to deliver the ſaid Garriſon, the Enemy came, and according to agreement, the ſaid Governour opened the Gates, and gave entrance &amp; poſſeſſion to the Enemy, who being poſſeſſed, in lieu of the reward promiſed, cauſed forthwith a Gallows to be erected upon one of the Rampiers, where the ſaid Governour was brought, and told by the chief of the Enemy, that he loved Treaſon, but hated the Traytor; ſaying further, If the ſaid Governor could not be faithful to his own Maſters for whom he had fought, how could he expect he ſhould be to him againſt whom he had ſo often ventured his life in ſeveral battels? And ſo cauſed him to be hanged.</p>
            <p>I ſhall leave the application to your ſelves, which undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will be your caſe and reward, if you betray your truſt and Country.</p>
            <p>Now for concluſion, to ſave your ſelves and friends in the three Nations from ruine take this ſhort Advice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let all your Regiments, Troops and Companies have Rendezvouzes; and if you do not camp in the Field, quarter cloſe together, and not ſo far aſunder as now you do; for you know that a bundle of Arrows divided aſunder are eaſier bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken than when bound together.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In immitation of former time, when you and the cauſe of the Nation was in as great danger as at preſent. And when many of your Officers had a hand in combining yours, and the Nations deſtruction, and that the ſame Game was then a playing which now is, you may remember what you then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59567:6"/> did at <hi>Newmarket</hi> and <hi>Tripoly-Heath</hi> Rendezvouze, you were not afraid of the Threats or frowns of any, but like brave re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Engliſh-men, made there choyce of ſome of your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Officers and Souldiers to be your Agitators, and to keep correſpondency one with another, and rejected ſuch as would then have betrayed you; do ſo now, and ſpeedily, more need now than ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When your Agitators are ſo nominated and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, let them conſider what is fit to be done, and preſented to your ſuperiour Officers for their concurrence, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive muſt be to this, or the like effect: That is to ſay, to frame an Engagement whereby you wil engage one to another not to ſuffer your ſelves to be disbanded, or divided, before ſuch time as the Government of the three Nations may be eſtabliſhed upon ſo firm fundamentals of freedome and ſafety, as thereby the Properties and Liberties of the people thereof, both as men and Chriſtians may be aſſerted and ſecured by their duely qualified ſucceſſive Repreſentatives in Parliament aſſembled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and without a King, ſingle perſon, or Houſe of Lords, and againſt all other the Enemies of the Commonwealth, and in particular againſt the return of any of the Family, or poſterity of the late King <hi>James,</hi> or King <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for encouragement to you in that bleſſed work, be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you will have Gods bleſſing, and for your aid and aſſiſtance, all the faithful of the three Nations; and although your Enemies by their tongues ſeem very numerous and bold, yet fear them not, for barking Curs never bites; nor indeed are they yet in a capacity to hurt you, as ſoon as they underſtand, or hear any ſtirring among you, their hearts faint, they are better at hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hawking, drinking healths and damnations, curſing and whoring, than they are at fighting; you have hitherto found them ſo, they are rather grown worſe and more cowardly than ever. It is ſeldome obſerved that an Enemy will ever ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that have ſo often beaten and conquered them when they were many thouſands in Field and Garriſons, you did not fear them; therefore be confident Gods Omnipotency is the ſame now and for ever, as at that time of calamity. It was, and you have the ſelf-ſame Cauſe, and I hope the ſame hearts and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59567:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> valour; and beſides in the eye of men far greater advantages by having all the Land and Sea Forces, Garriſons, and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of War of all ſorts, which your Enemies have not, all their noiſe and hopes will ſoon vaniſh. If you will no longer dally with them, therefore ſtand to your Arms and be doing, or elſe you will never be able to hinder and eſcape the Roaps that are now a Twiſting, nor the Gallows that are ſetting up for the Executions of you and your friends. Remember the Proverb, <hi>Men Armed, are ſeldome harmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59567:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
